

# Vignesh Baskaran

# Fullstack Developer(Backendheavy)

vignesh865@gmail.com +91 7010795244

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/vb865 Medium: https://medium.com/@vignesh865 Github: https://github.com/vignesh865

Multi-faceted software engineer with 5+ years of professional experience in developing highly usable enterprise microservices, won hackathons and elite medals in application development, looking for a highly competitive workplace to enhance my skills and grow along with the company and its vision.

### **Key Skills**

- Java 11 +
- Spring framework and spring boot
- Python
- Django
- Javascript
- React
- DB MySQL, Mongo, Cassandra, Redis and Elastic search
- AWS ELB, Lambda, EC2, Cloudwatch, Cloudfront and Aurora
- Worked in Microservices, Containers and Kubernetes.
- Queuing systems RabitMQ, Amazon Sqs and Apache Kafka.

# **Professional Experience**

#### Software Development Engineer II

Omuni, Bangalore, Karnataka | March 2021 - Present

- Developing solutions with high scalability, distributed, and fault tolerance in mind.
   Creating tech designs, and implementing new product features by being the owner of a set of microservices.
- Important Milestone: Developed a Spring boot Mongo DB-powered analytics
  dashboard service that processes 30M+ events from the Kafka queues on a daily
  basis. Generated revenue of USD 40K+ and saved 45 man-hours on a monthly basis
  with faster bug resolutions and a 90% reduction in escalations.
- Important Milestone: Developed DB-independent archival application that archives any table by detecting the relationship between all the dependent tables automatically. It can also archive from multiple DBs. It works at any scale, in other words, the number of data won't limit this application. It was archived 46 lakh data with this app in production. Configurable via Jenkins as well.
- Important Milestone: Built asynchronous reporting framework using message queues, push notifications, multi-threading, and bucketing patterns in MongoDB.
   Reported data with a scale of 200K+ in 3 minutes that increased transparency of the inventory management system which reduced customer support tickets by 55%.
- Important Milestone: Created ELK multi-cluster setup stack with Filebeat, Logstash, and Elasticsearch to ship log data from different microservices and store it in an auditable format.
- Important Milestone: Designed a highly scalable file processing system with a
  poller-consumer structure that allows customers to update a large number of
  inventory data into our system via files. Around 3 lakh data will be there per file
  and 100+ files will be uploaded daily and processed via the newly designed system.
- Important Milestone: Introduced swagger code generation and OAS specifications inside the development process. Developed code plugin which allows integrating swagger codegen in the build and provides a faster learning curve for other devs.
- Important Milestone: Revamped the entire inventory management system service which was messy and troublesome earlier and transformed that into a readable and efficient system along with introducing new features in the roadmap.

#### Fullstack Engineer (Backend-heavy)

Locus, Bangalore, Karnataka | June 2019 - March 2021

- Converting product spec to tech designs to production-ready code with spring framework. Experienced in SQS, Queue worker, Cloudwatch, RDB, and ELB.
   Monitoring build and Deployment in various micro-services hosted in AWS. Fixing bugs as an on-call.
- Important Milestone: Developed an algorithm with the basis of k-means clustering
  and traditional window technique for cleaning the continuous stream of locations
  which processes more than a lakh of records per day and filters out invalid
  locations with more than 95% accuracy.
- Important Milestone: Developed generic SMS integration framework which allows integrating any SMS provider like kaleyra, mailgun, etc just with a JSON configuration instead of adding separate code implementation. Reduced new integration dev effort to 0 and time to instantaneous.
- **Important Milestone**: Created automation API for the tour and bulk task creation which leads to lower effort and time for the customer success team.
- **Important Milestone:** Created around 96+ screens for an internal dashboard which is made of Python-Django.

#### Software Engineer

Infoview Technologies, Chennai, Tamilnadu | September 2017 - June 2019

- Created high-performance enterprise Apis with spring framework.
- Important Milestone: Created performant enterprise APIs in the Business
   Performance Management and SCM- Procurement domain having a latency of less
   than 1 in handling ~2M, daily.

- Important Milestone: Fixed codes and carried out capacity estimations for migrating a database from Cassandra to MySQL Deployed the application with 55% more efficiency within a stipulated time of 2 months.
- Important Milestone: Developed a POC in order to detect churning customers based on past customer activities with 97% accuracy by employing multiple ML and Visualization methodologies.

# **Thoughts**

What's the hardest problem you've solved?

**Situation**: It was difficult to display the real-time position of a rider and present location trails to the warehouse managers on the rider tracking software.

**Task:** This was a problem because, at times, the location data received from the rider's GPS to the backend was stale, random, or fixated on a single point.

**Action:** To resolve the problem, we developed an algorithm on the basis of k-means clustering, traditional window, and Graph techniques for cleaning the continuous stream of locations.

**Result:** This processed 1B+ records on a daily basis and filtered out invalid locations with more than 95% accuracy for displaying the real-time position.

What are you most excited to work on for the next couple of years?

I look forward to gaining expertise while working as a product architect and developing highly scalable systems.

Also, I wish to manage the entire Product Development Life-Cycle from its inception to its delivery and strengthen my vision of working as a Product architect in the future.

## Accomplishments

- Won 2nd runner up in National Level hackathon held by Government of India An android application that detects impersonation in examination using Aadhar data
- Elite medal in Modern Application Development A course hosted by Indian Institute of Technology

#### **Education**

August 2013 - June 2017

Bachelor of Technology in Information Technology Anna University, BIT campus